Guide to the Frank Percy Wilson Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frank Percy Wilson Papers
1912-1962
OSB MSS 157
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
13.13
(28 boxes)
The Frank Percy Wilson Papers contain correspondence, research files, and notes for articles and projected longer works, including an edition of Tabacco; the British Academy biography of E. K. Chambers; and works on Elizabethan vocabulary and proverbs.
Wilson, F. P. (Frank Percy), 1889-1963
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased by James Marshall Osborn from Mrs. Frank Percy Wilson, 1963; bequest of James Marshall Osborn, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Frank Percy Wilson (1889-1963)
Frank Percy Wilson was born in Birmingham, England, the youngest of nine children. He took a first class in English (1911) and an M.A.(1912) at the University of Birmingham, and a B.Litt from Lincoln College, Oxford in the following year. Wilson's thesis was on Thomas Dekker. He volunteered for the Army in September 1914, and was badly wounded at the battle of the Somme in July 1916, spending over a year in the hospital and enduring repeated surgeries. After brief service as the Minister of Food, he returned to his scholarly career. Wilson was appointed as a university lecturer at Oxford in 1923, and as reader in 1927. He was subsequently professor of English at the University of Leeds (1929-1936); Hildred Carlisle Professor of English Literature at Bedford College, London (1936-1947); and finally Merton Professor of English Literature at Oxford (1947-1957).
Wilson's academic specialty was Elizabethan language and literature, and he published many papers and articles on the subject during his lifetime, including Illustrations of Social Life, Shakespeare and the New English Bibliography, The Jestbooks of the Sixteenth and Early Seventeenth Centuries, Shakespeare and the Diction of Common Life, and Shakespeare and the New Bibliography. From 1935 on he served, with Bonamy Dobrée, as general editor of the Oxford History of English Literature. His own volume in the series, English Drama 1485-1585, appeared posthumously in 1969, edited by G. K. Hunter. He also served as general editor of the Malone Society from 1948 until 1960.
Wilson married Joanna Perry-Keene, one of his Oxford students, in 1924; the couple had four children. Joanna Wilson shared his interest in Elizabethan proverbs and sayings, and worked with him for many years to prepare the third edition of the Oxford Dictionary of Proverbs (1970), which was published after Wilson's death with her introduction.
Scope and Contents
The Frank Percy Wilson Papers document part of Wilson's scholarly career and include research correspondence and subject files, particularly for articles and papers on Shakespearean topics and on the book Tabacco. Also included are a large alphabetical file of notes for various publication projects; research material for the Facsimile of the Shakespeare First Folio and the British Academy biography of Sir E. K. Chambers; papers relating to the estate of fellow Shakespearean Walter Wilson Greg; and seventeen boxes of note cards and note slips on Elizabethan words and word usage.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence and Research Notes, 1912-1961. II. W. W. Greg's Publications and Estate, 1924-1961. III. Miscellanous Notes, undated. IV. Research Cards, undated. V. Research Slips, undated.
Early printed books; English drama -- Bibliography; English drama -- Early modern and Elizabethan, 1500-1600; English literature -- Bibliography; Publishers and publishing -- Great Britain; Scholars; Chambers, E. K. (Edmund Kerchever), 1866-1954; Chapman, R. W. (Robert William), 1881-1960; Davin, Dan, 1913-1990; Ferguson, F. S. (Frederic Sutherland), 1878-1967; Greg, W. W. (Walter Wilson), 1875-1959; McManaway, James Gilmer, 1899-1980; Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616 ( Bibliography); Shipton, Clifford Kenyon, 1902-1973; Smith, David Nichol, 1875-1962; Wilson, F. P. (Frank Percy), 1889-1963; Wilson, John Dover, 1881-1969; Knapp-Fisher, James S.; Bibliographical Society (Great Britain); Janson, Cobb, Pearson and Co
- Correspondence and Research Notes, 1912-1961; Series I; 3.13; (9 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains extensive correspondence and notes on the articles Illustrations of Social Life, Shakespeare and the New English Bibliography, The Jestbooks of the Sixteenth and Early Seventeenth Centuries, and on the book Tabacco. Also included are a large file of notes for various projects, and research material for the Facsimile of the Shakespeare First Folio and the British Academy biography of Sir E. K. Chambers.
  - General
    - Notes and correspondence relating to "Illustrations of Social Life," The Plague in Shakespeare's London; notes on Shakespeare, Spenser, Donne and ms. plays, 1912-1960 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - Photostats and facsimiles, printed articles and reviews, correspondence and notes on almanacs, prognostication, and miscellaneous projects, 1912-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
      - A-C (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
      - D-G (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
      - H-M (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
      - N-R (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
      - S-Z (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - "Shakespeare and the New Bibliography"
    - Misc MS notes for article (few typed) (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Greg, Sir Walter Wilson
      ALS to F. D. Wilson
      1942 June 15, Petworth, Sussex
      2 p. 23 x 18 cm
      Approves piece in present form (criticism attached)
      1942 June 22
      2 pp. 25 x 20 cm Petworth, Sussex
      General remarks about early Shakespeare critics,
      texts, editors
      1942 July 7, Petworth, Sussex
      12 p. 25 x 20 cm Petworth, Sussex
      General remarks on Shakespeare texts
      1942 Sept 6, Petworth, Sussex
      Queries about imprints; returns typescript (not
      included)
    - Ferguson, Frederick Sutherland
      LS to F. P. Wilson
      1942 June 30, London
      2 p. 26 x 20 cm
      Remarks on chapters 2 and 3; question on Richard
      Jones as painter
    - Pollard, Graham
      ALS to F. P. Wilson
      1942 May 30, Oxford
      1 p 26 x 20 cm
      Offers criticisms on piece
      1942 June 12, N/P
      4 p. 26 x 20 cm
      Reacts to several of Wilson's comments
    - Smith, David Nichol
      1942 June 21, Oxford
      20 p. 21 x 13 cm
      Detailed criticisms of piece
      1942 July 7, Oxford
      16 p. 21 x 13 cm
      Detailed criticisms of paper
    - Wilson, Frank Percy
      ALS to David Nichol Smith
      Asks for criticisms of sections 2, 3 of piece
      (typescript wanting)
      1942 July 5, Cambridge
      3 p. 26 x 20 and 21 x 13 cm
      Enclosed (wanting) part 6 of piece for criticisms
  - "The English Jestbooks.. ."
    Full citation for this article is: "The English
    Jestbooks of the Sixteenth and Early Seventeenth
    Century" HLQ ii, 121-158
    - Misc. MS notes (few typed) relating to Compilations for article (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 9 misc. bookseller catalog pages
    - Davis, Godfrey
      1938 Oct 4, San Marino
      1 p. 26 x 21 cm
      1938 Oct 27, San Marino
      4 p. 26 x 21 cm (with enclosures)
      1938 Nov 16, San Marino
      1938 Dec 16, San Marino
      2 p. 26 x 21 cm
    - Hamilton, George L.
      1938 Sept 1, Cambridge, Mass.
      Remarks on Madmen of Gotham (1619)
    - McManaway, James Gilmer
      1938 June 20, Washington
      3 p., 26 x 21 cm
      Answers queries on English jest books; asks for
      information on Mother Shipton
      1938 Aug 17, Washington
    - Nicholon, [Frank Carr?]
      1938 Jan 6, Edinburgh
      1 p. 18 x 13 cm
      Answers Wilson's query on "A Foole upon Foole"
    - Wright, Lyle Henry
      1938 June 28, San Marino
      Is unable to aid him in request
  - Tabacco
    - Wilson, F. P. ed., Tabacco, Oxford; Basil Blackwell & Mott, Ltd, 1961 [An annotated proof copy] (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Shipton, Clifford K.
      1958, Sept 5, Worcester, MA
      1 p. 22 x 14 cm
      Reports that 1595 Tabacco was sold to Rosenbach Co.,
      which sold it to Arents Collection
    - Jackson, William Alexander
      1961, Feb 18, Cambridge, MA
      1 p. 31 x 19 cm
      Speculates on Huntington copy of Chute's Tabacco
    - Dickson, Sarah Augusta
      1960 Nov 9, New York
      3 p., 21 x 14 cm
      Remarks on Arents copy of Tabacco and related works
    - Blackwell, Basil
      1960 Feb 16, Oxford
      1960 Nov 9, Oxford
      1960 Nov 16, Oxford
      1 p. 25 x 21 cm
    - Fry, Mary Isabel
      1960 Oct 15, San Marino
      Gives details of Huntington copy of Tabacco
    - Halliday, Eleanor
      1960 Sept 20, Oxford
      1 p. 20 x 13 cm
    - British American Tobacco Company Limited, Report & Accounts 1960 [issued Feb 27, 1961]
    - 66 pages of MS notes for Tabacco and concerning aspects of tobacco
    - 5 pages of photostatic reproductions of 1595 edition
    - Sotheby's catalog, pp. 49-50, 3 May items.
    - Library Call Slip, Calling for The Armes of the Tobachonists (1630)
    - 5 p. misc. catalog pages and prints
  - "Table Talk"
    - MS notes and quotations for "Table Talk"--including notes on Johnson, Boswell, Addison, James I, Pope, Richardson, others (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Leverhulme Reaserach Fellowships
      LS (by unidentified person) to F. P. Wilson
      1940 Nov 27, Watergate, Blackfriars
      1 p. 13 x 20 cm
      Thanks for reprint of "Table Talk"
    - Literary and Philosophical Society
      LS (by unidentified librarian) to F. P. Wilson
      1940 Apr 20, Newcastle upon Tyne
      1 p., 26 x 21 cm
      Information on Robert Spence Watson Memorial Lecture,
      1931
    - Davies, Godfrey
      1940 May 24, San Marino
      1 p 26 x 21 cm
      Reports that he is pleased to print "Table Talk"
    - Crissey, M. H.
      1940 June, San Marino
      2 p., 20 x21 cm
      Corrections to "Table Talk" noted
    - ALS from unknown writer
      1940 Apr 23, Oxford
      7 p., 21 x 13 cm
      Praise and Queries for "Table Talk"
    - Clippings, TLS 11 June 1931 and 14 March 1935
  - Facsimile of Shakespeare First Folio
    - Davin, Daniel Marcus (Box 9, Folder 3)
      1951 Aug 9, Oxford
      Responds to comments on reproduction techniques in
      facsimile samples
      1951 Aug 15, Oxford
      1 p. 17 x 21 cm
      Comments on size of pages and method of reproduction
      1951 Nov 21, Oxford
    - Wilson, Frank Percy
      AL to D. M. Davin
      N/D, Oxford
      3 p., 18 x 11 cm
      Comments on specimen pages
    - Six specimen pages (annotated)
  - British Academy Biography of Sir E. K. Chambers
    - 40 Pages of MS notes concerning Chambers [2 are annotated by J. D. Wilson] (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 2 pages of Typescript draft [Annotated by T. D. Wilson]
    - Blackwells catalog 606, pp. 17-18 [Contains books by Chambers]
    - Obituary, TLS 1954, ? 22
    - Newspaper clippings from Times and TLS, 1940-1945 [several relate directly to Chambers]
    - Chambers, E. K. Review of George Gascoigne, Elizabethan Courtier, Soldier and Poet pp. 125-26
    - 8 pages of MS notes in Chambers's hand
    - Wilson, Frank Percy
      ALS [draft] to F. P. Wilson
      1955 Sept 11, Middle Carn
      Notes on Chambers, esp. work on Coleridge
      1956 Oct 11, Middle Carn
      4 p., 26 x 21 cm
      Response and criticism of biography
      1956 Oct 14, Middle Carn
      Comments on revisions to biography
      1956 Oct 26, Middle Carn
      Further comments on biography
    - Harley, ?
      1956 Sept 21, London (letter attached)
    - Twentyman, A. F.
      1955 July 6, Styhgate
      2 p. 18 x 14 cm
      Regrets being unable to say anything about Chambers
    - Wheeler, Sir Mortimer
      1956 Oct 24, London
      1 p., 23 x 18 cm
      Thanks for biography
    - Chambers, Lady Eleanor (Nora)
      1956 Oct 20, Poutrailas
      2 p. 18 x 12 cm
      Answers Wilson's questions on husband's portrait
    - Davin, Daniel Marcus
      1956 Oct 17, Oxford
      Gives details on Chambers
    - Wilson, John Dover
      1954 Dec 8, Balerno
      1956 Jun 23, Balerno
      1956 Jul 29, Balerno
      1956 Aug 29, Balerno
      1956 Sept 21, Balerno
      1956 Oct 2, Balerno (LS-typed)
      1956 Oct 10, Balerno
      1956 Oct 15, Balerno
      1956 Oct 18, Balerno
      1957 Jan 15, Balerno (LS typed)
    - D. M.
      ALS (frag)
      N/D
      Probably details relating to life of Chambers
    - Chapman, Robert William
      ALS to E. K. Chambers (postcard)
      1941 Feb 22, Park Town
      Textual Notes to ?
- W. W. Greg's Publications and Estate, 1924-1961; Series II; 2
  This series contains documents relating to the settlement of the estate of Shakespeare scholar Walter Wilson Greg (1875-1959); Frank Percy Wilson was one of the executors of his will.
  - Income and expense account, 1924-1933, for English Literary Autographs, 1550-1650. 1 p., 21 x 26 cm. [with copy] (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Royalty statement for half-year ended 31 Dec, 1960
  - Royalty statement for half-year ended 30 June, 1960
  - 10 MS pages of notes for Shakespeare quarto editions
  - One catalog leaf, pages 20-21
  - Childs, C. E. N.
    LS to W. W. Greg
    1959 June 17, London
    1 p. 21 x 17 cm
    Request to microfilm section of Henslowe Papers
  - Roberts, R. J.
    1959 June 22, London
    Thanks for reproduction permission of Henslowe
    Papers
  - Davin, Daniel Marcus
    1959 Jan 12, Oxford
  - Gosling, Bernard
    1959 May 22, Oxford
    Comments on Shakespeare quarto fascimiles
  - Dafford, J. W. P.
    1959 10 April, London
    Requests to buy a number of Greg's books
  - Keep, G. P.
    1960 Sept 13, Oxford
    Comments on English Literary Autographs, 1559-1650
    LS to E. M. Dring (copy)
    1960 Nov 15, Oxford
    Concerns stock and prices of )English Literary
    Autographs 1550-1650)
  - Elizabeth, J. M.
    ALS to F. P. Wilson [David]
    1960 Dec 7, Oxford
    4 p. 18 x 14 cm
    His comments on royalty check and problems with
    Greg's estate
  - Knapp-Fisher, James S.
    1959 June 26, London
    1 p., 21 x 13 cm
    Publication offer for Greg's Pastoral Poetry and
    Pastoral Drama
    1959 2 July
    Publication details for Greg's Pastoral Poetry and
    1959 6 July
    1 p. 21 x 13 cm
    Publication details, and method of reproduction
    1959 13 July
    Publication details, and offer to publish The
    Henslowe Diaries v. II
    1959 15 July
    1960 15 August
    Permission to microform The Henslowe Diaries
    1961 May 30, London
    Royalty payment from Russell & Russell
  - Greg, Lady Elizabeth
    1959 Mar 18, Petworth, Sussex
    3 p., 18 x 13 cm
    Thanks for visit and management of Greg's library
  - Newsam, Peter
    1959(?), Mar 18, Oxford
    1 p., 18 x 13 cm
    [attached to LS from M. F. Pearson]
  - Pearson, Michael F.
    1959 Mar 17, London
    1 p. 21 x 18 cm.
    Concerns Greg's personal papers
  - Brown, John
    Letter (by secretary) to Messrs Janson, Cobb, Pearson
    & Co.
    1959 July 28, Oxford
    Request to reprint 670 lines of "A Critical Mousetrap"
    Firm of Janson, Cobb, Pearson & Co.
    1859 Mar 18, London
    Reference to Greg's will
    Letter to F. P. Wilson
    1959 Mar 23, London
    Assignment of Wilson as literary executor
    1959 June 15, London
    Duties as executor
    1959 July 29, London
    Reference to letter of 15 June
    1959 Aug 18, London
    Deed of assignment enclosed for signature
    1959 Sept 15, Lond
    Deed of Assignment enclosed for signature
    Parolow, B. M.
    LS to Messrs Janson, Cobb, Pearson & Co.
    1959 June 10, London
    Reports request of Russell & Russell to publish
    Pastoral Poetry and Pastoral Drama
    West, O. B.
    1960 Aug 8, London
    Asks permission to xerograph sections of Greg's books
    (permission form enclosed)
    1960 Sept 28, London
    Thanks for permission to publish
    Cain, P. L.
    1 p. 18 x 21 cm
    Royalties check correction notice
    University Microfilms Ltd.
    1961 May, London
    Royalty check for U. S. A. sales
    8 invoice forms from University Microfilms, Inc.
    Newspaper announcement of Greg's will
- Miscellaneous Notes, undated; Series III
  Included here are notes on printed books and
  manuscripts; Stationer's Registers; sales, public and
  private; and collections, public and private in England
  and the United States
  - Notes on Stationer's Registers 1557-1639 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Rawlinson MSS F (Poetry) at Bodleian (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Notes on Tanner MSS 167-169 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Notes on Guildhall Library MSS and misc. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Privy Council Register, 1612-31 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Ashmole Mss 36, 37, 38, 857, 1030, 1147 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Huntington Chronological Catalog (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Misc. notes on MSS and printed books held by private collectors in England and U. S. A.; sale catalogs. (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Notes relating to Dekker's works (bibliographical) (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Misc. notes on public library collections of MSS and printed books (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Notes on texts and classification records from Public Record Office, esp. Court of Chancery records (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Research Cards, undated; Series IV; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  This series contains 3x5" index cards with annotations in F. P. Wilson's hand on thousands of Elizabethan words and phrases. The notes were perhaps compiled as part of his research on Elizabethan word usage and phraseology. Boxes 11-15 are in roughly alphabetical order; Box 16 and Box 17 are each in alphabetical order as well.
  - A - Coxcomb (Box 11)
  - Cozen - Hungerly (Box 12)
  - Holland, Hugh - Pack-penny (Box 13)
  - Pacalet - Spettle (Box 14)
  - Spiders' webs - Zone (Box 15)
  - Academic plays-Yver, Jacques (Box 16)
  - APES - Yver, Jacques (Box 17)
- Research Slips, undated; Series V; 5.83; (10 boxes)
  Series V contains 5x7" paper slips with annotations in F. P. Wilson's hand on thousands of Elizabethan words and phrases. The notes were perhaps compiled as part of his research on Elizabethan word usage and phraseology. Many of the slips are on previously used letterhead and contains portions of letters, article drafts, bills and other documents on their reverse sides. Boxes 18-21 appear to be in a single alphabetical order; the remaining boxes appear to be in roughly alphabetical order within each box.
  - Anchor - Cockalondlinge wake (Box 18)
  - Daglings - Gentilize (Box 19)
  - Gentlecraft - Musician (Box 20)
  - Musk - Tony (Box 21)
  - Penny raised... - Zisia (Box 22)
  - P. 36 - Yeoman 4 (Box 23)
  - As dry as a kex - Plays and Players 36 (Box 24)
  - Audeley - Integrate, witty and (Box 25)
  - Colaois- To be in a tale (Box 26)
  - FOOD - Twenty... (Box 27)